You can see there's basically a disturbance
right here in the Force, which I think is very interesting.
the model release, we believe, caused a severe degradation
in the amount of times these static files were getting called on.
Why has there been almost a 50% decrease in the amount of times
the agents use these specific instruction files?
no. Oh!
Nice to see everybody today.
At this beautiful event.
Thank you, Tessl.
Thank you, Sam, for the invite.
So this talk is named 'Steer.'
'Steer' refers to coding agents.
Steering capability.
We'll talk about that at length.
And we'll talk about how the multi-agent coding
agents are breaking agile.
So let's do some background.
Here's me and some of my team.
My name is Guy.
I'm the co-founder and CEO of Baz.
I've been hacking at this specific problem space for almost seven years.
So my last company started in 2019.
In the midst of the digital transformation.
So as all of us were moving from on premises
into cloud-hosted web applications, me and my team, some of them
in this picture we discovered one tiny problem
is that everybody's adopting new coding paradigms, new programming
languages back in the day called Terraform and CloudFormation and Kubernetes,
but are also causing many misconfigurations and vulnerabilities
that are exposing their customers' private data.
So we spun up in.
De facto standard for scanning
that type of infrastructure as code for misconfigurations and vulnerabilities.
It's been a success to date.
It has 6 million monthly downloads up until today.
We built a company around it.
It was called Bridgecrew, ran for about a year and a half
and then got acquired by Palo Alto Networks, where me and again,
this beautiful team built an application security business
that still runs, pretty amazing products today out of Palo Alto,
securing over 50% of the Fortune 50.
And scaling every single year.
I left Palo Alto about two years ago to start Baz because
we saw that this problem is getting worse.
So just like digital transformation introduced a new paradigm,
which was new programming languages that were completely overlooked by the existing
software development stack.
AI coding is now introducing
a millions, trillions of lines of code that no one's really looking at, right?
We did some past work on this specific area,
also had some patents registered, and we're still contributing.
Me and my team today contribute to many open source projects you all know and love.
Basically, to tackle this specific problem.
So like any good
community talk, we're going to start with the famous Spider-Man meme.
And the reason me and other speakers love this meme,
because it really points to a problem that we have or re observed now
as, engineers and software developers, how many software developers
do we have in the room today? Right. Good.
Which we're not really sure today what's
driving our code into a single specific direction.
So we have a semblance of what's driving, but we don't really know.
I haven't labeled the Spider-Men, because there are different flavors today,
but you can think of them as, you know, Claude, OpenAI, Cursor.
You can think of them as AGENTS.md,
CLAUDE.md, and a skills file, right?
So there's different ways
where we can give instructions to our coding agents and get to a result,
but we don't really know who's in the helm.
I'm not sure if any of you have ever looked, but over the last year
and we'll see some data.
This talk is mostly around data,
and it's supposed to make you freak out, by the way.
The way that your coding agents ingest
these steering files, this configuration files, has changed multiple times.
So originally, like almost 14, 16
months ago, we first started to adopt AGENTS.md files.
So who uses an AGENTS.md or a CLAUDE.md?
So, like a static instruction file, because we identified
or I should say anthropic identified
that we're inserting the same context over and over again in our coding agents.
So they made us hardcode these instructions onto our repositories.
And what they basically did in the first iteration is
they loaded up into the context window over time, the way that context was loaded
into your coding agents session changed dramatically.
So, starting with the Opus 3.7 family,
we observed that they start to compact the AGENTS.md files
because we started to see so many of these files reminisced,
remaining the code base, and start to steer in different directions.
Once we got skills added to the mix, we found that they are actually
inserting it in a separate part of the of the context window of your coding agent.
So today, no one really knows, but we're seeing much better
results in terms of adherence to a steering agent, a specific one.
But there's still many, many problems left to solve.
I'm going to use a couple of
modestly viral tweets
to prove my point, but none of them really reflect your reality.
I think it's a reality that sometimes exists on social media.
Number one, and there's a, I think,
almost a consensus around where the bottleneck is today.
So there's generally no,
restraint or there's no stopping a developer once
they get their hands on a coding model.
We have great free coding models that can help us now compose code
at endless amounts.
The way this leads me
and my team is really commonly think about collaboration, right?
So the stock starts with agile.
If you think about where we started this journey into a coding
3 or 4 years ago, it was in an environment where we had rituals,
where we synchronized humans on what we're going to build next.
A lot of these rituals are now thrown out the window.
And the bottleneck that once existed, which is a human led
bottleneck of having enough engineers on a given problem, has now shifted.
And the bottleneck, I think, commonly
now referred to as the PR bottleneck, basically talks about the fact
that we're able to build and ship many new paths.
But the way that our current systems are wired, those are not the bottleneck.
Right?
Because we have 60 systems that take, you know, between
tens of minutes to hours to complete their cycles.
And obviously, we still rely on our peers to get validation
that what we're writing is legitimate.
Second degree to this problem is what happens
not only in a team environment,
but what happens when there's more than one agent at play.
So I talked about this kind of referenced this on the Spiderman slide,
but there's now some concrete research that goes into understanding what happens
when there's more
than one active coding session in a given code base or a code repo.
So let's even assume that
those specific agents use the same operating system.
They all use either a single harness or drive their skills
from a single registry or.
Their their coding trajectories
has nothing to do with those agents and files and instructions at all.
It has to do with the shared memory, the context that's being traversed,
that's being fetched from your code base, on every on, on every code base session,
on every coding session can radically change
the type of plan you might get when you do a Claude Code plan
and the type of output when you try to build something new.
Now that seems like a new answer, like a small thing.
But if we can't really get, you know, consistent confidence
that we're going to get a result, a code that's going to adhere to
what's important for us in a steering file, then what are we even doing?
Right?
This is one final bit of research and then we'll go into data.
So there's ways where we can see that coordination
actually does compound and create value.
Interestingly, neither a
an instruction or a skill
and not even a shared memory creates a consistent outcome.
The number one factor that drives a consistent outcome is setup.
So if we're able to create setups that mimic the exact starting point
for a given coding task, that's probably the number one predictor
that we get a consistent results on the back.
Okay.
So this data has a bit of a backstory.
So what does Baz do?
Baz operates
simply a fleet of agents
that performs code review in very specific subdomains.
Now this is important just because I want you to understand
the weight I'm going to give the data.
I'm going to show you
and what I think that teaches us about where the industry is headed.
So we've built out these domain specific agents
that are think of them as experts, domain experts with superpowers
that are bound to solve specific problems within your SDLC.
So one example is a security reviewer.
is powered by a prompt factory
that continuously defines prompts that are relevant
for your codebase and the problems and the vulnerability that it may be,
prone to and continuously tries to identify.
What would an attacker do if he identifies your code as an opportunity
to attack your current application?
So it has its own prompt factory.
It has its own tools, so it's able to run things like compilers,
interpreters, code scanning tools like static analysis and dynamic analysis.
It's able to go into your dependency registries
and unpack your your dependencies and a bunch of other things
and their kind of claim to
fame is the ability to see whether or not your peers are exploitable.
Now, we do this for a bunch of different types of subdomains.
Whenever we produce a suggestion, whether that's shipped through a GitHub
or GitLab comment, we retain your response as a developer.
So if you accept the comment or if you've implemented the change
that we suggested, we label that as a success for the agent,
and we know that this specific prompt, with the specific context, works for you.
Same works the opposite way.
We sometimes
see profanity, so someone curses the agent because they give them a bad response.
Great indication.
Keep cursing agent.
We know that this agent is not doing a very good job.
Yeah. Now, the way we collect
data, we're trying to understand how people are building.
And specifically, we want to see what's effective in how they're building.
So this becomes and we've been doing these use cases for about two years now
for our customer base.
And now we have an anonymous database that teaches us
how people are reacting to the feedback they're getting from
these different agents.
And that gives us an indication whether or not their steering
engine is contributing for them.
Writing good, compliant, correct, not buggy code,
rather than using bad
configurations or bad instruction files.
Okay,
so the first data point is not even about data point.
Anybody familiar with Tessl's skills registry?
So sorry for the maybe dropping in a a competitor here.
So Tessl's registry — an online registry — has what's most interesting for me,
is trend data for what people are downloading into their
installs.
And, and probably this is largely skewed into people that are building harnesses.
Right.
So if you are building a harness, you're iteratively updating the scale,
just like you would iteratively import a package from npm.
So two things that are interesting here.
The first one is you'd see that out of the top ten a lot of them are code
review skills.
So interestingly enough, people want guidance
even if they feel very confident about their code base.
So they go out to the internet and they ask people like Matt Packer
for, templated instructions on how to do good code review.
The other thing you might notice is that most of the download
on this two time period is flat.
So I think it's starting to tell us something about the adoption of skills.
So keep that in mind as well.
But still all of these skills and all of the other skills are in the other tabs.
You can go go ahead and look for them.
I think they give us a good sense, a good, sentiment
into what the coding agents are good at at every given point.
So, like four months ago, everybody was looking for skills that, helped you this.
Love your product. Copy.
A couple of months before that, everybody wanted good skills
that make sure that your design system isn't drifting.
But now we've kind of generalized on some best practices across
different domains like front end, back end, etc..
Okay,
so this is the first part of
of some proprietary.
Metadata.
And there's another question here.
You can see there's basically a disturbance
right here in the Force, which I think is very interesting.
So we track
the usage of these different instruction files across our customer base.
And you can see we look at a bunch of different types of
static raw files that you would store in your code base.
You can see that the most prevalent was Claude.
And that's because Anthropic still forces you to use that.
But right after that we see skills.
So these are kind of the top to use.
And then there's a wide variety
like Cursor rules, and CodeRabbit, and a few others.
What do you think happened here
I guess.
Yeah.
It was a model. Yeah. Great job.
Okay. We're going to do like a point system.
So you got a thousand points.
So there was a model release I think slightly before here.
That's why the dates are skewed.
And the model release, we believe, caused a severe degradation
in the amount of times these static files were getting called on.
And since this is a very diverse codebase, mostly enterprise customers,
it's really hard to kind of take out one specific takeaway.
But I think this was completely invisible to you.
And I mean, we saw this in the data.
And after what does this mean?
Why has there been almost a 50% decrease in the amount of times
the agents use these specific instruction files?
Again, this is going to be a confusing term.
This is not supposed to instill confidence in you
second or third graph right now.
So we have this way to see whether or not our agent suggestions
are getting picked up and addressed by humans or coding agents.
And this approach shows you two different lines across this past summer,
which had multiple meaningful model releases, by the way, no skewing models here.
And you can see, basically, the amount of times
that we got addressed comments with guidelines and without guidelines.
So what we saw is that when agents adhere to coding guidelines,
like the ones that exist in those instruction files,
we see that eventually there's stronger acceptance from developers.
So it's a strong correlation. So what happens?
People write their instruction files.
Our agents pick them up.
And then there's strong
adherence and acceptance of of those findings specifically.
So it means that when we do specifically try to find
problems and bugs using their instructions and skills.
The baseline model adheres to them.
And we're seeing better acceptance rates, with that in mind.
We also saw a
correlation where coding guidelines correlate with higher review acceptance.
So we produce a review comment. We tell you.
Hey there's going to be a bug here.
There's going to be a vulnerability.
And we identify then whenever we include your own guidelines, either
in the language or the sentiment,
there's a stronger likelihood that developers will use it.
Now, this doesn't work with a stock harness — like your stock harness.
If you use Claude Code, you don't get this.
This happens with our harness because we force the model to use your guidelines.
Because we saw this data back in the beginning of the summer,
that whenever we include language that exists in your instruction files,
there's a higher likelihood that it will get picked up.
We think it's correlation.
We have some examples that it's not causation.
Yeah.
So, what's the takeaway from this?
So one thing to think about when you think about writing your own
your own harness, your own AGENTS.md,
your own skills registry — is to really think deeply.
If you are in a position where you can continuously maintain
the knowledge and information that's stored in that file.
Because what happens is, regardless whether or not it was updated recently,
other coding agents, downstream, and Baz is no different
than a GitHub Copilot, and it's no different than a CodeRabbit or a Cursor.
They are going to pick up on that little nuance and assume
that's still a single source of truth for you.
What's the inverse version of that?
If you have skills, you have guidelines.
You have instruction files, especially in a big team in a large mono repo.
And they weren't updated in the last six, 12, 18 weeks.
And you didn't specifically call them out on another,
kind of central control plane for your AI,
whether it's your own harness or like a global ruleset,
then you're going to get a self-correcting agent
that's continuously adhering to that old agent stack,
even if it's no longer relevant, even if sometimes
you've made other decisions downstream that don't necessarily reflect that.
And one final one just to close this off.
So again, this data is supposed to be confusing.
We discovered that some specific coding instructions
correlate stronger to high acceptance.
So specifically, one of our competitors is called CodeRabbit.
They actually use a structured JSON that contains a rule set.
Has anyone used CodeRabbit?
Yeah.
So CodeRabbit specifically, we discovered that their rule
set across models and across organizations
is specifically strong at forcing your agents to do something.
So even if you did like a poke or like a 14 day trial a year ago,
and this file still exists in your code base, it's
going to overcome the instructions in your CLAUDE.md, your latest skills.
And even if you move to Cursor or an AGENTS.md.
Right.
So think about the hydra problem here, and how much that makes a difference.
Okay.
So to wrap this up I want to send you off with two things.
We started with steer steer and age. So.
If it was on a board
then someone would pick it up and the task would get done.
We had rituals like a daily or weekly or a retrospective
where we talked about the good and the bad practices that we want to
distill into our knowledge bases and into our engineering habits.
Those are gone.
I would say that across
maybe thousands of teams that we've seen.
Those rituals are diminishing, in the sense
that — are they really determining what the engineering outcomes are going to be?
So what replaced them?
Three main things.
If I have to be very, very general.
The first one is spec.
So huge growth in spec files.
Spec files written either in markdown or linked to a Linear issue.
And by the way, plan files as well.
Like planning, and planning through Claude Code.
Those are probably the number one ways to make
your coding agents act in a specific vertical.
Collaboration over planning.
Not completely solved today with Claude Code,
but there is a good open source solution you should check out — Plane.
As an example, we have some capability over there,
but you'll be amazed at how much a good human written
spec impacts outcome
regardless of the underlying configuration mess.
Number two is verification.
Obviously I'm biased because that's my day job.
I've been doing this for seven years, but if we identify GitHub as like
this choke point, that's really important for us for decision making.
If we built the tools into either a GitHub Action or,
or a stock tool, where you get that verification,
you'll be able to suppress bad behaviors that result from steer slips.
Number
three is and this is quite new is merge tactics.
So historically, we'd write, right?
We would squash and merge the diffs into our main branch.
I would strongly recommend looking at creative merge tactics.
Merge queues are now native to GitHub.
So that's not even a niche product anymore.
Anyone can use them.
And what merge queues specifically allow you to do.
And there's different ways to go about it.
It allows you basically to cherry pick much better than before
and be able to understand whether or not, especially if you wrote a good spec,
what you eventually want your code to include.
So, you know, one thing we're seeing is that it probably doesn't make sense.
It's probably almost like a hopeless goal.
You're not going to have the best hygiene on your coding
agent operating system, just because this environment is moving very fast.
One thing that we recommend to
our customers is to think, rethink about collaboration and agile
through these three specific lenses, which we think are still top of mind
for companies,
especially if you're building something like a software factory.
But even if you're doing some baseline modernization around the code agent.
And that's it.
If this is interesting for you.
There's one asset I would recommend checking out at baz.ai.
It's called the Rework Calculator.
And what the Rework Calculator allows you to do is —
You can plot in your team size
and your average PR rates, and it will give you a sense
of how much work and how much money you're spending on iterative rework
that goes into some of these, redundant workflows as a result of
multiple operating systems and inconsistent coding agent activity.
So we have a full report
called The State of Rework, and you can check that out on our website.
Okay.
Perfect on time.
Almost.
Okay. Thank you. Thank you.
We have time for questions.
In a true story time
as live streaming and being in the room, you will hold two microphones.
Do any questions about.
Yes. No.
I'm still.
Two mikes a week.
Thank you so much for the talk.
That was really interesting.
The data specifically was quite fascinating
because we've seen very similar trends and we've in our evaluations
seen the exact regression that you were seeing as models change.
And so it was very refreshing to see that that kind
of validated in your data as well, which is
in a separate lens as well.
So my main question is,
as you're seeing these models change and improve,
are you still seeing — even when the files setting
get cut down for the guidance and the improvement for the code reviews?
Towards the end, I saw that there was still a bit of an uptrend, right?
Like we're still now compounding and adding more files and stuff.
Do you see that on average decreasing, or do we still see it going back to levels
where the guidance that we're adding into our code bases is just different?
Maybe less prescriptive or even more specific.
Like, how's it changing as the models are getting better?
I'll tell you why — that's the exact question
that freaks me out and freaks some of our customers out,
because there's anecdotal evidence that that's exactly what's happening.
So later model versions are better
at adhering to baseline instructions.
Let's call them.
But the problem, I think, is that we never pin to a specific model.
So think about even today, especially
at the meta level, like the Opus 5 models came out,
we very rarely used the same model throughout our coding journey.
We would usually start a, you know, plan with maybe
get bigger model.
Then, you know, another model
maybe doesn't have that problem because you have great investors.
But many, many of us and many of our customers have that.
The reason is that
the inconsistency has too many variables.
So the models are constantly changing under the hood,
the operating systems and the paradigms are changing under the hood.
And my concern is that the labs are not very transparent
about how they ingest and inject, that type of context in and out of the session.
So even if I want to make a bold
investment and say, you know, our team is going to be completely
invested in skills and build their own skills registry.
But OpenAI then comes out with a model that does a better job
at compaction and injecting,
you know, skills into the context session,
but we don't know how they do it on the file level, on the folder level, on
the repo level, that I think it's still a big mystery.
And people are going to have to figure it out
whether it works out for their code base or not.
And the problem is that we don't have good visibility to adherence at the moment.
Great question though.
Did you ever have that?
You know, you posted this
because if you see some interference, I will stand in the way.
We were briefed.
So my question is there's a lot of other things that go into it,
like, say, long-horizon projects and a setup where you might have,
certain types of agents splitting up the work and even the harness.
Right.
So if you use, like, DeepSeek, to have your own setup,
how should we think about interpreting,
kind of the data that we've seen so far
and maybe what to expect that might change
or just, you know, how do we think about that additional complexity?
Yeah. Great. Great point.
So the question was on a long-horizon task.
We have one good example that's pretty consistent.
We've been doing full code base sweeps for a good part of the last ten months.
So like a chunky database that gives us an indication on whether
or not models and instruction files are really adhering, in the long horizon.
Much more consistent than shorter tasks.
And we have a reason to think why that's happening
just because of the amount of turns
and iterations, there's just a larger likelihood that your coding agents
are going to land on the right instruction file within that longer time period,
but we're seeing a sharp decrease on the user side.
So users don't want to spend a lot of time coding.
They're expecting faster responses.
They don't want to use those expensive and long-horizon models right now.
So I feel like the trade-off right now is between
you know, longer horizon, like, go on this board.
Side quests probably get better adherence, but on the other hand,
I think the developers downstream don't really want that.
They want fast
responses, they want faster verification, they want to close faster loops.
And that's where these problems are really at their worst.
Good question.
Thank you so much.
More questions? Awesome.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Sam.
Thank you so
Oh, no. Oh!